<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"

	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The Shona People	</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description>A detailed history of the Shona people of Zimbabwe</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 06:24:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.2.2</generator>
			<item>
				<title>
				By: myfootpaths				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-14698</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[myfootpaths]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 06:24:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-14698</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I have one issue with most narrations that try to bring in the convergence of the People and the First People generally known and understood as the Bantu and the San. There is the belief that there was enslavement of the San by the Bantu but no one ever provides evidence of such enslavement. I believe there is need to trace people&quot;s totems. I have heard in oral history the totem VaMbwetete refers to the female organ and also linked to the San or Khoisan who call themselves the First People. It would seem that there was basically marriage alliances as male hunters moved southward as scouts for land.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have one issue with most narrations that try to bring in the convergence of the People and the First People generally known and understood as the Bantu and the San. There is the belief that there was enslavement of the San by the Bantu but no one ever provides evidence of such enslavement. I believe there is need to trace people&#8221;s totems. I have heard in oral history the totem VaMbwetete refers to the female organ and also linked to the San or Khoisan who call themselves the First People. It would seem that there was basically marriage alliances as male hunters moved southward as scouts for land.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: ra				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-608</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ra]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 00:41:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-608</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[look into the Yoruba word ochun or oshun     and  the kamitic hetheru]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>look into the Yoruba word ochun or oshun     and  the kamitic hetheru</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: ra				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-607</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ra]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 00:35:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-607</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[shona word for more insight  look into  the Yoruba word oshun or  ochun]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>shona word for more insight  look into  the Yoruba word oshun or  ochun</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: David				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-603</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 19:24:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-603</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[But how does bukala fits in all of the information you produced]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>But how does bukala fits in all of the information you produced</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: MuUngwe				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-287</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[MuUngwe]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 06:17:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-287</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[The word &quot;Shona&quot; comes from &quot;Svina&quot;, a Shona word which means a person who squeezes intestines and cleans them for his meat. When the well-to-do slaughtered their livestock for meat, they offered poor people the intestines. The word evolved to describe poor people in general... individuals, families and villages... whom they called &quot;MaSvina&quot; in Shona. It was so common that explorers, hunters, missionaries and anyone else who lived long enough among the MaShona picked it up. They in turn used it as a collective term for all the people we call MaShona today.

The Ndebele origin of this word is very doubtful. They may have used it in the same sense when comparing their cattle wealth to that of the MaShona but it hardly refers to a coward. In fact there had to be people in Matebeleland itself in those days who would also fit this description. If the AmaButho intended to to deride what they perceived as Shona cowardice they had far more creative words they could use.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The word &#8220;Shona&#8221; comes from &#8220;Svina&#8221;, a Shona word which means a person who squeezes intestines and cleans them for his meat. When the well-to-do slaughtered their livestock for meat, they offered poor people the intestines. The word evolved to describe poor people in general&#8230; individuals, families and villages&#8230; whom they called &#8220;MaSvina&#8221; in Shona. It was so common that explorers, hunters, missionaries and anyone else who lived long enough among the MaShona picked it up. They in turn used it as a collective term for all the people we call MaShona today.</p>
<p>The Ndebele origin of this word is very doubtful. They may have used it in the same sense when comparing their cattle wealth to that of the MaShona but it hardly refers to a coward. In fact there had to be people in Matebeleland itself in those days who would also fit this description. If the AmaButho intended to to deride what they perceived as Shona cowardice they had far more creative words they could use.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Ndabezinhle				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-286</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ndabezinhle]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2015 10:00:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-286</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Shona means a coward who runs and hides in Mountain caves in Ndebele. The shona used to run and hide in the mountain when attacked by Ndebele amaButho and they sayed &quot;amagwala abaleka ayoshona embalwini zentaba” hence the name AmaShona]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Shona means a coward who runs and hides in Mountain caves in Ndebele. The shona used to run and hide in the mountain when attacked by Ndebele amaButho and they sayed &#8220;amagwala abaleka ayoshona embalwini zentaba” hence the name AmaShona</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mushawasha				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-285</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mushawasha]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2015 05:26:31 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-285</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Shona traditional religions are oftenly confused with afterlife. Shonas believed in god called mwari who created people however they didnt believe that mwari needed appeasement therefore theywere not religious in the judeo-sense god woship was limited to rainmaking ceremonies. But shonas believed that when you die you become a spirit and leave in a spirit relm where you could be summoned through a spirit medium(a living person you choose) or a spirit doctor aka witch doctor and it was believed that you could protect your own   from bad spirits, so shonas were mainly controlled though mediums but did not worship dead people in a religious sense, they just treated dead people as if they were still alive and a bit more powerful]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Shona traditional religions are oftenly confused with afterlife. Shonas believed in god called mwari who created people however they didnt believe that mwari needed appeasement therefore theywere not religious in the judeo-sense god woship was limited to rainmaking ceremonies. But shonas believed that when you die you become a spirit and leave in a spirit relm where you could be summoned through a spirit medium(a living person you choose) or a spirit doctor aka witch doctor and it was believed that you could protect your own   from bad spirits, so shonas were mainly controlled though mediums but did not worship dead people in a religious sense, they just treated dead people as if they were still alive and a bit more powerful</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mushawasha				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-284</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mushawasha]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2015 05:08:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-284</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[What people dont understand is that shona people did not really have tribes pre colonial. They were dzinzas- people of the same totem wich could be loosely termed tribes however these were actually extended families (brothers, sister&#039;s uncles and tete) but people of the same totems could hail from different nations (called nyika) i.e soko murehwa could be from hwedza(svosve), harare(chishawasha), chivi(mahugwi), murehwa, different autonomous states from one tribe. Zezuru for example was just a language not a tribe e.g mhofu and soko are not related tribe wise even though they all spoke zezuru, but were related through intermarriages since it was taboo to marry from your lineage. When BSAC settled in mashonaland no body attacked them because nobody had felt invaded. Zezuru states were only responsible for their nations l.e chiefs only protected their villages and did not interfere outside their boundaries. Zezurus only started fighting when they were told tho move from their land and even then it was one village for itself, the only time the zezurus decide to fight as a group was when they were told to pay hut tax and one chief had been whipped for failing to tell authorities that his cattle had rinderpest and even then they fought anonymously not with a joint comand. The first person to unite shonas was a british scholar who created syllables for shona basing it on zezuru since it was impractical to have written language for every dialect, he chose the word shona citing that it was of nguni or ndebele origin]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What people dont understand is that shona people did not really have tribes pre colonial. They were dzinzas- people of the same totem wich could be loosely termed tribes however these were actually extended families (brothers, sister&#8217;s uncles and tete) but people of the same totems could hail from different nations (called nyika) i.e soko murehwa could be from hwedza(svosve), harare(chishawasha), chivi(mahugwi), murehwa, different autonomous states from one tribe. Zezuru for example was just a language not a tribe e.g mhofu and soko are not related tribe wise even though they all spoke zezuru, but were related through intermarriages since it was taboo to marry from your lineage. When BSAC settled in mashonaland no body attacked them because nobody had felt invaded. Zezuru states were only responsible for their nations l.e chiefs only protected their villages and did not interfere outside their boundaries. Zezurus only started fighting when they were told tho move from their land and even then it was one village for itself, the only time the zezurus decide to fight as a group was when they were told to pay hut tax and one chief had been whipped for failing to tell authorities that his cattle had rinderpest and even then they fought anonymously not with a joint comand. The first person to unite shonas was a british scholar who created syllables for shona basing it on zezuru since it was impractical to have written language for every dialect, he chose the word shona citing that it was of nguni or ndebele origin</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: owen				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-283</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[owen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 12:36:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-283</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[the word shona comes from the ndebele word entsshonalanga, which means people from the east  (remember the ndebele settled in the south west of zimbabwe). before the collective name shona people were known more by their ethnological groupings zezuru, karanga, korekore etc. this is why even in modern day zim people talk of kuita chikaranga/chizezuru etc but never chishona.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>the word shona comes from the ndebele word entsshonalanga, which means people from the east  (remember the ndebele settled in the south west of zimbabwe). before the collective name shona people were known more by their ethnological groupings zezuru, karanga, korekore etc. this is why even in modern day zim people talk of kuita chikaranga/chizezuru etc but never chishona.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Mashona Marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-282</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mashona Marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2010 22:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-282</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[The Maker Thanks for the new information on the Shona People. Can you tell me were the Shona and Mashona name came from? I have read all of the post and no real good news!King Shona]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Maker Thanks for the new information on the Shona People. Can you tell me were the Shona and Mashona name came from? I have read all of the post and no real good news!King Shona</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: The Maker				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-281</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[The Maker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2010 18:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-281</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Correction on the second paragraph should read, ‘he land which the Ndebeles occupied was definitely not under the shona people- this is also evidenced by lack of documented history on wars, if there are any, that Mzilikazi fought with them (Shonas) until they succumbed to the Ndebele.’ An on the third from last paragraph to read, ‘The truth being there are no Shona people reminants in Matabeleland,’]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Correction on the second paragraph should read, ‘he land which the Ndebeles occupied was definitely not under the shona people- this is also evidenced by lack of documented history on wars, if there are any, that Mzilikazi fought with them (Shonas) until they succumbed to the Ndebele.’ An on the third from last paragraph to read, ‘The truth being there are no Shona people reminants in Matabeleland,’</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: The Maker				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-280</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[The Maker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2010 17:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-280</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[In as much as I do no have the proper history of Zimbabwe I do not believe the so called Shona people occupied and ruled the whole land that is now between Zambezi and Limpopo instead evidence point out that they stretched their domain to Mozambique where probably lies their roots. The land which the Ndebeles occupied was definitely under the shona people- this is also evidenced by lack of documented history on wars, if there any, that Mzilikazi fought with until they succumbed to the Ndebele. Surely if the Munhumutapa empire was that big they I do not think they would have been defeated an ‘invading’ Ndebele people under Mzilikazi who was on the run and had fewer ‘soldiers’. Evidence to suggest my line of thinking is to be found in the naming of historical places like Njelele, Khami and Dlodlo which are clearly not Shona names. Before the coming of whites the land between these two above mentioned rivers was known as the Matabele nation and whites will confess to that. What is more blacks did notuse rivers as boundaries, a thing which was introduced by the whites. If Matabeleland region was already occupied how would Mzilikazi have fled to it. By inference the truth could that the whole of the Southern Africa was under the Zulu kingdom and probably Mzilikazi fled across Limpopo cause he probably new of the existence of the unocupied land. If the Shonas were indeed rulers of the land between the two rivers I do not they were so stupid as not to see the goodness of the land and build up their bases there. The truth being there are Shona people reminants in Matabeleland. And they the shona know this that ukuna matongo avo kunoku. The system of governance employed by Shaka has some biblical origin in the sense of Kings. This is no surprise when we look at the distance between Ethiopia and Zimbabwe. The latter according to genesis of the bible was the largest chunk of the garden of Eden that it had to be watered by two first rivers that were created by God:rivers Pishon and Gihon. Do not hide the truth and do not glorify lies about who are the owners of the land between the two rivers. Both the Shona and Ndebeles or indeed Kalanga or other tribes found in Zimbabwe today can equal claim a stake. Otherwise the land belong to all of us according to our areas of dominance, that is Matabeleland or Mashonaland. As to who built the great Zimbabwe it is anybody’s guess we can nit be so sure that it is Shonas as basically besides the monumental structure there are traces of evidence to suggest that such kinds of structures was their way of life. The monument was a one off event per se and does not in any way identify with ordinary Shona way of living even today! So please stop these unfounded glorifications and start looking for your answers from the proper Bible not another Kings James’s Opinion of the Bible.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In as much as I do no have the proper history of Zimbabwe I do not believe the so called Shona people occupied and ruled the whole land that is now between Zambezi and Limpopo instead evidence point out that they stretched their domain to Mozambique where probably lies their roots. The land which the Ndebeles occupied was definitely under the shona people- this is also evidenced by lack of documented history on wars, if there any, that Mzilikazi fought with until they succumbed to the Ndebele. Surely if the Munhumutapa empire was that big they I do not think they would have been defeated an ‘invading’ Ndebele people under Mzilikazi who was on the run and had fewer ‘soldiers’. Evidence to suggest my line of thinking is to be found in the naming of historical places like Njelele, Khami and Dlodlo which are clearly not Shona names. Before the coming of whites the land between these two above mentioned rivers was known as the Matabele nation and whites will confess to that. What is more blacks did notuse rivers as boundaries, a thing which was introduced by the whites. If Matabeleland region was already occupied how would Mzilikazi have fled to it. By inference the truth could that the whole of the Southern Africa was under the Zulu kingdom and probably Mzilikazi fled across Limpopo cause he probably new of the existence of the unocupied land. If the Shonas were indeed rulers of the land between the two rivers I do not they were so stupid as not to see the goodness of the land and build up their bases there. The truth being there are Shona people reminants in Matabeleland. And they the shona know this that ukuna matongo avo kunoku. The system of governance employed by Shaka has some biblical origin in the sense of Kings. This is no surprise when we look at the distance between Ethiopia and Zimbabwe. The latter according to genesis of the bible was the largest chunk of the garden of Eden that it had to be watered by two first rivers that were created by God:rivers Pishon and Gihon. Do not hide the truth and do not glorify lies about who are the owners of the land between the two rivers. Both the Shona and Ndebeles or indeed Kalanga or other tribes found in Zimbabwe today can equal claim a stake. Otherwise the land belong to all of us according to our areas of dominance, that is Matabeleland or Mashonaland. As to who built the great Zimbabwe it is anybody’s guess we can nit be so sure that it is Shonas as basically besides the monumental structure there are traces of evidence to suggest that such kinds of structures was their way of life. The monument was a one off event per se and does not in any way identify with ordinary Shona way of living even today! So please stop these unfounded glorifications and start looking for your answers from the proper Bible not another Kings James’s Opinion of the Bible.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Mashona Marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-279</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mashona Marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2010 00:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-279</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I read a book from the libary and caome across a African King that had a name with 16 letters in it that had the name Shona in the middle. It was in the year 950?]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read a book from the libary and caome across a African King that had a name with 16 letters in it that had the name Shona in the middle. It was in the year 950?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: murambatsvina				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-278</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[murambatsvina]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2010 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-278</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Im not aware of the existence of such a king. Where did you get that from?]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Im not aware of the existence of such a king. Where did you get that from?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Mashona Marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-277</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mashona Marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2010 23:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-277</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[King MaShona- who was he?]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>King MaShona- who was he?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: murambatsvina				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-276</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[murambatsvina]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2010 16:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-276</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I stumbled on this website as i was juss searching for some stuff. I would like to clarify to you all shona people abt the origins of the word shona.When the ndebele people were migrating from kwazulu they were always on a war path, they fought battles with every tribe they encountered on their way, eg the sothos, tswanas, kalanga etc.Now when they made peace with the kalangas in the present day matebeleland, their next target for raiding were the karangas, zezuruz, nyikas( basically the current shona tribes). what used to happen was that all the time when they were raiding these tribes, the people would dissapear into mountain caves and they never used to be able to figure out where exactly these people were hiding. Now this act of hiding in Ndebele/zulu was called “ukushona”, so they would ask each other “bashonephi labantu”. never mind the current diluted zulu known to you as ndebele, the original ndebele was zulu and instead of tsh- they used sh.Everytime they would find themselves asking “bashonephi” and eventual they called them ama”shona” because these people used to just dissapear (shona/tshona) into the curves.it was not a deregatory term as one of the fools was suggesting above, it was just a reference term. Now this is how we know it thina besintwini. No hard feelings people pliz, I know we hate each other already.lol.Anywhere you got your revenge thru gukurahundi right, luckily i survived that one. But gukurahundi was different in that it was killing aimed at eliminating our ndebele tribe from the face of the world in the 20th century, where as then thina we were just raiding cattle and ofcourse woman, or and some man to reinforce our armies. and ofcourse the traditional healers, you guys were gifted so we would bring those aboard as well.but i think we are square now, gukurahundi vs our raiding, what do you think vanha vachangamire? lol. Hey can you tell me more about nyatsimba mutota, what was he up there before we came by the way?One more thing i would like to know, its these nehanda and kaguvi thugz. what exactly did they do besides witchcraft?? lol.I need to visit chipinge i heard the manyika guys are gurus in witchcraft, but why cant they take out this zezuru that orchestrated gukurahundi kanti? You makarangas, are you sure you are the ones that built the great zimbabwe? what do you know about the lembe people you guys? If you really built the great zimbabwe then you had power and skill, hats off for you. But i dont trust you, for you have failed to run what is originally yours, zimbabwe.lol. zvogbo was tried and failed.What i have noticed though is that the name shona really unites you people especially against us the ndebeles, you forget we live with your cousins the kalangas, vendas and tongas. Infact they also dont like you,lol.Till we meet again in another gukurahundi, take care. Note: i did not call anyone “svina”, can i hear an “amen” from my mashonaland bretheren. ok ok before i close what does svina mean? and the other thing ndebele is a name we were also given by the tswana people albeit not for hiding curves during fights but for our prowess in using ihawu, the sheild, thats what they called litebele.By the way you were not the only ones that suffered at our, even the zulus themselves. the only bast*rds that annahilated us were yuropiyenz. Mugabe has sorted them for us though,lol.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I stumbled on this website as i was juss searching for some stuff. I would like to clarify to you all shona people abt the origins of the word shona.When the ndebele people were migrating from kwazulu they were always on a war path, they fought battles with every tribe they encountered on their way, eg the sothos, tswanas, kalanga etc.Now when they made peace with the kalangas in the present day matebeleland, their next target for raiding were the karangas, zezuruz, nyikas( basically the current shona tribes). what used to happen was that all the time when they were raiding these tribes, the people would dissapear into mountain caves and they never used to be able to figure out where exactly these people were hiding. Now this act of hiding in Ndebele/zulu was called “ukushona”, so they would ask each other “bashonephi labantu”. never mind the current diluted zulu known to you as ndebele, the original ndebele was zulu and instead of tsh- they used sh.Everytime they would find themselves asking “bashonephi” and eventual they called them ama”shona” because these people used to just dissapear (shona/tshona) into the curves.it was not a deregatory term as one of the fools was suggesting above, it was just a reference term. Now this is how we know it thina besintwini. No hard feelings people pliz, I know we hate each other already.lol.Anywhere you got your revenge thru gukurahundi right, luckily i survived that one. But gukurahundi was different in that it was killing aimed at eliminating our ndebele tribe from the face of the world in the 20th century, where as then thina we were just raiding cattle and ofcourse woman, or and some man to reinforce our armies. and ofcourse the traditional healers, you guys were gifted so we would bring those aboard as well.but i think we are square now, gukurahundi vs our raiding, what do you think vanha vachangamire? lol. Hey can you tell me more about nyatsimba mutota, what was he up there before we came by the way?One more thing i would like to know, its these nehanda and kaguvi thugz. what exactly did they do besides witchcraft?? lol.I need to visit chipinge i heard the manyika guys are gurus in witchcraft, but why cant they take out this zezuru that orchestrated gukurahundi kanti? You makarangas, are you sure you are the ones that built the great zimbabwe? what do you know about the lembe people you guys? If you really built the great zimbabwe then you had power and skill, hats off for you. But i dont trust you, for you have failed to run what is originally yours, zimbabwe.lol. zvogbo was tried and failed.What i have noticed though is that the name shona really unites you people especially against us the ndebeles, you forget we live with your cousins the kalangas, vendas and tongas. Infact they also dont like you,lol.Till we meet again in another gukurahundi, take care. Note: i did not call anyone “svina”, can i hear an “amen” from my mashonaland bretheren. ok ok before i close what does svina mean? and the other thing ndebele is a name we were also given by the tswana people albeit not for hiding curves during fights but for our prowess in using ihawu, the sheild, thats what they called litebele.By the way you were not the only ones that suffered at our, even the zulus themselves. the only bast*rds that annahilated us were yuropiyenz. Mugabe has sorted them for us though,lol.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Mashona Marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-275</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mashona Marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2010 15:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-275</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Gonmazana, your thoughts were right. Nobody really knows the ‘true’ meaning of MASHONA OR SHONA…Mashona Marsh]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Gonmazana, your thoughts were right. Nobody really knows the ‘true’ meaning of MASHONA OR SHONA…Mashona Marsh</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mashona marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-260</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mashona marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 01:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-260</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[kuda-RIGHT ON! Please contact me. ‘mashona marsh’]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>kuda-RIGHT ON! Please contact me. ‘mashona marsh’</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mashona marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-252</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mashona marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 01:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-252</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[please contact me for more review on your coments? My name is Mashona Marsh in texas-usa, Hel pme with more in for please…]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>please contact me for more review on your coments? My name is Mashona Marsh in texas-usa, Hel pme with more in for please…</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mashona marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-249</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mashona marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 01:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-249</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[please!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>please!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mashona marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-243</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mashona marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 01:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-243</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Please let me know what you know about the ‘shona’. How did this name start? Who was named SHONA FIRST? My name is Mashona Marsh in Texas…usa]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Please let me know what you know about the ‘shona’. How did this name start? Who was named SHONA FIRST? My name is Mashona Marsh in Texas…usa</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mashona marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-239</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mashona marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 01:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-239</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Please contact me about wahr you have found out anout the ‘shona’ peoples. My name is ‘Mashona Marsh’ yes A male in Texas]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Please contact me about wahr you have found out anout the ‘shona’ peoples. My name is ‘Mashona Marsh’ yes A male in Texas</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Gonmazana				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-274</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gonmazana]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2010 21:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-274</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Indeed nobody knows the origins of the name nor it’s meaning. Many continue to speculate though. Sometimes though when enough people buy into a particular line of speculation it boarders on ‘reality’ even in the absence of absolute truth.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Indeed nobody knows the origins of the name nor it’s meaning. Many continue to speculate though. Sometimes though when enough people buy into a particular line of speculation it boarders on ‘reality’ even in the absence of absolute truth.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Mashona Marsh				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-270</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mashona Marsh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2010 20:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-270</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Hey you are right! Were did the real name come from. I have the name and people alway ask. Who wad the first Shona?. Was he a Africian King! I call My self ‘KING SHONA’]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hey you are right! Were did the real name come from. I have the name and people alway ask. Who wad the first Shona?. Was he a Africian King! I call My self ‘KING SHONA’</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Gonmazana				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-273</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gonmazana]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2010 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-273</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I think you are 100% correct in your various statements that as yet no substantial evidence hasbeen furnished on the origins of the name. All we know is that it pops up somewhere in the mid to late 1800s. Someone else argued with me above that the Shona never assimilated the Khoisan. That person is partly correct however, the ancestors of the modern day Shona/Bantu replaced and assimilated s group of hunter gatherers who may or may not have been Khoisan but most certainly remarkably similar. These people notonly hunted and gathered food but made many rock paintings as well another aspects of their culture bearing similarities to the Khoisan. This is attested to by archeological evidence much of which still exists today at various locations around the country. Granted these hunter gatherers may have been a lot less populous than the ones eventually encountered by the Ngunigroups further south]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I think you are 100% correct in your various statements that as yet no substantial evidence hasbeen furnished on the origins of the name. All we know is that it pops up somewhere in the mid to late 1800s. Someone else argued with me above that the Shona never assimilated the Khoisan. That person is partly correct however, the ancestors of the modern day Shona/Bantu replaced and assimilated s group of hunter gatherers who may or may not have been Khoisan but most certainly remarkably similar. These people notonly hunted and gathered food but made many rock paintings as well another aspects of their culture bearing similarities to the Khoisan. This is attested to by archeological evidence much of which still exists today at various locations around the country. Granted these hunter gatherers may have been a lot less populous than the ones eventually encountered by the Ngunigroups further south</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: lucas mbambo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-272</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[lucas mbambo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2010 12:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-272</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[vamwe tava kunakidzwa nemanyepo.mashingaidze,dont lie to foreigners.shona given to european or americans as a name is hebrew name and translates to God is gracious.it has no link whatsoever to the shona tribe. shona has been linked by some historians to the name sena.it has also been linked to the name svina.both assumptions have not been verified. the tshona theory is popular but likely to be wrong as i have argued above.i want to credit the white settlers with the creation of the shona people not coining the name.my understanding is there was no reference to shona people at all prio to colonisation.there were the fragmented tribes that now claim to be collectively shona.this was made stronger by the rhodesian education system which found a common ground for the tribes and came up with some academic language called standard shona.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>vamwe tava kunakidzwa nemanyepo.mashingaidze,dont lie to foreigners.shona given to european or americans as a name is hebrew name and translates to God is gracious.it has no link whatsoever to the shona tribe. shona has been linked by some historians to the name sena.it has also been linked to the name svina.both assumptions have not been verified. the tshona theory is popular but likely to be wrong as i have argued above.i want to credit the white settlers with the creation of the shona people not coining the name.my understanding is there was no reference to shona people at all prio to colonisation.there were the fragmented tribes that now claim to be collectively shona.this was made stronger by the rhodesian education system which found a common ground for the tribes and came up with some academic language called standard shona.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Oswell Dhlembeu				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-245</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Oswell Dhlembeu]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2010 06:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-245</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Thanks Nhuma yaMambo but don’t you think Karanga too has some few clicks and they maybe very original such as in “kudla”?]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks Nhuma yaMambo but don’t you think Karanga too has some few clicks and they maybe very original such as in “kudla”?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Oswell Dhlembeu				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-256</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Oswell Dhlembeu]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2010 06:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-256</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Lucas Mbambo my brother tell me more. You seem to have a new dimension that I never know and its interesting that you say Rozvi is separate from both Kalanga and Shona and you I liked your example of vuma balanda. I think this debate will be enriched with such divergence of views.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lucas Mbambo my brother tell me more. You seem to have a new dimension that I never know and its interesting that you say Rozvi is separate from both Kalanga and Shona and you I liked your example of vuma balanda. I think this debate will be enriched with such divergence of views.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Gonmazana				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-271</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gonmazana]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 09:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-271</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Another legend speaks of the Ngni groups having named the Shona by virtue of their location to the west of their new settlement and obviously nothing could be further from the truth, they were actually located in the opposite direction. Archeological evidence points at a complete abandonment of what are now the Great Zimbabwe ruins hundreds if years before the arrival of the Ndebele following the collapse of the dynasty that used it as their capital. This nicely summarized ‘history’ gives the impression that the settlement was abandoned following the arrival if the Ndebele. In fact the raids by the Ndebele have from time to time Bern exaggerated when in fact they numbered bonnier than five at selected settlements. There are many Karanga/Shona groups who never came into contact with these raiding parties further inland and to the north. It is in the interests if a racist agenda that these have been painted in the most barbaric all encompassing terms western historians gave painted them. Further, this summary suggests that most of the Karanga were absorbed/assimilated by the Matabele, how laughable. Ask Ministers Mudenge, Cde Hungwe, PM Tsvangirai if indeed they are Ndebele if you disagree. The group that experienced some assimilation were the Kalanga who have really not been Karanga for several hundred years, well since the later stone age.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Another legend speaks of the Ngni groups having named the Shona by virtue of their location to the west of their new settlement and obviously nothing could be further from the truth, they were actually located in the opposite direction. Archeological evidence points at a complete abandonment of what are now the Great Zimbabwe ruins hundreds if years before the arrival of the Ndebele following the collapse of the dynasty that used it as their capital. This nicely summarized ‘history’ gives the impression that the settlement was abandoned following the arrival if the Ndebele. In fact the raids by the Ndebele have from time to time Bern exaggerated when in fact they numbered bonnier than five at selected settlements. There are many Karanga/Shona groups who never came into contact with these raiding parties further inland and to the north. It is in the interests if a racist agenda that these have been painted in the most barbaric all encompassing terms western historians gave painted them. Further, this summary suggests that most of the Karanga were absorbed/assimilated by the Matabele, how laughable. Ask Ministers Mudenge, Cde Hungwe, PM Tsvangirai if indeed they are Ndebele if you disagree. The group that experienced some assimilation were the Kalanga who have really not been Karanga for several hundred years, well since the later stone age.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Gonmazana				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-269</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gonmazana]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 09:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=79#comment-269</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Human beings at times tend to have this insatiable quest to explain things even where the answers are not within grasp. The truth of the matter is even though we know the name ‘Shona’ cropped up sometime after the arrival of the Nguni (soecifically Ndebele group) there is no reliable record of how this name came about nor do we know it’s meaning. There are various versions including the one you give here as well as that the Shona used to disappear in caves while escaping from the raiders leading to them saying ‘batshona’ phansi. How exactly they could untraceably conceal themselves, entire village settlements together with their livestock remains a mystery.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Human beings at times tend to have this insatiable quest to explain things even where the answers are not within grasp. The truth of the matter is even though we know the name ‘Shona’ cropped up sometime after the arrival of the Nguni (soecifically Ndebele group) there is no reliable record of how this name came about nor do we know it’s meaning. There are various versions including the one you give here as well as that the Shona used to disappear in caves while escaping from the raiders leading to them saying ‘batshona’ phansi. How exactly they could untraceably conceal themselves, entire village settlements together with their livestock remains a mystery.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
			</channel>
</rss>
