<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"

	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The Rozvi Empire	</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description>A detailed history of the Shona people of Zimbabwe</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 04:39:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.2.2</generator>
			<item>
				<title>
				By: From Monomotapa to Modjadji, The Rise of A Queen &#8211; Tales From Modjadji				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-22589</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[From Monomotapa to Modjadji, The Rise of A Queen &#8211; Tales From Modjadji]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2019 04:39:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-22589</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[[&#8230;] Also read ./../index.html [&#8230;]]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Also read <a href="./../index.html" rel="nofollow">./../index.html</a> [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Chamunorwa Gatawa				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-21608</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chamunorwa Gatawa]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 23:20:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-21608</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Remember we have the karanga (vhitori)from Masvingo and the kalan&#039;ga from ntababaezinduna stretching to Botswana andSA these are two different  tribes]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Remember we have the karanga (vhitori)from Masvingo and the kalan&#8217;ga from ntababaezinduna stretching to Botswana andSA these are two different  tribes</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: mtyambizi				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-20547</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[mtyambizi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 23:15:36 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-20547</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Well done baba...]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well done baba&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Sekemutema				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-4516</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sekemutema]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 15:26:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-4516</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[True that. You can see the statue of the Zimbabwean bird in Ancient Egypt]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>True that. You can see the statue of the Zimbabwean bird in Ancient Egypt</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Canisios Chibaya				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-723</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canisios Chibaya]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 12:52:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-723</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Some of these people claiming to be historians are not to blame, they were taught, they don&#039;t know but they were made to believe they now know. The real story cannot be traced properly now because a lot of distortion has taken toll due to the western influence designed to mislead and confuse, all leading to continued argument and civil war. In the Zimbabwe of today, many claim to have been rulers because of the abundance of these distortions.

When the Whites came into this country (I&#039;m was informed by my grandfather) they didn&#039;t start by waging wars against all.They sweet-talked all and made friends out of many, after which they gathered information, learned the differences that existed between and among the rulers and the ruled, and all other small tribes that had long been absorbed by larger and powerful tribes. They then played intermediary role listening to both fabricated and actual claims and facts from all sides. They then used those differences to create civil wars supporting both sides weakening them at the same time. Soon they after they took over with very little resistance. Thus, they then widened the gape naming the two strong holds as Matebeleland and Mashonaland respectively. They recruited Police Officers from Mashonaland and deployed them in Matebeleland with an instruction to ill-treat the Ndebele-speaking natives while those recruited from Matebeleland were deployed in Mashonaland with the same instruction. This went on to further deepen hatred between the two.

From their fabricated stories they crafted what we call history today which suffers from propaganda and hate stuff. All tribes were made to believe they were once rulers, the hated tribes were direct descendants of the  Rozvi rulers and up to this date,I don&#039;t know where exactly my great sekuru &quot;Bhasvi&quot; was buried. All they say is his grave is in Bulawayo at Mathonjeni, their capital city was at Khami and that they went to Church (Njelele) to praise Musikavanhu.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some of these people claiming to be historians are not to blame, they were taught, they don&#8217;t know but they were made to believe they now know. The real story cannot be traced properly now because a lot of distortion has taken toll due to the western influence designed to mislead and confuse, all leading to continued argument and civil war. In the Zimbabwe of today, many claim to have been rulers because of the abundance of these distortions.</p>
<p>When the Whites came into this country (I&#8217;m was informed by my grandfather) they didn&#8217;t start by waging wars against all.They sweet-talked all and made friends out of many, after which they gathered information, learned the differences that existed between and among the rulers and the ruled, and all other small tribes that had long been absorbed by larger and powerful tribes. They then played intermediary role listening to both fabricated and actual claims and facts from all sides. They then used those differences to create civil wars supporting both sides weakening them at the same time. Soon they after they took over with very little resistance. Thus, they then widened the gape naming the two strong holds as Matebeleland and Mashonaland respectively. They recruited Police Officers from Mashonaland and deployed them in Matebeleland with an instruction to ill-treat the Ndebele-speaking natives while those recruited from Matebeleland were deployed in Mashonaland with the same instruction. This went on to further deepen hatred between the two.</p>
<p>From their fabricated stories they crafted what we call history today which suffers from propaganda and hate stuff. All tribes were made to believe they were once rulers, the hated tribes were direct descendants of the  Rozvi rulers and up to this date,I don&#8217;t know where exactly my great sekuru &#8220;Bhasvi&#8221; was buried. All they say is his grave is in Bulawayo at Mathonjeni, their capital city was at Khami and that they went to Church (Njelele) to praise Musikavanhu.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Canisios Chibaya				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-722</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canisios Chibaya]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 05:14:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-722</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I&#039;m Bhasvi (Chibaya) from Wedza. Comparison of what I&#039;m reading here to what I gathered from some elders that I happened to share time with only shows a very interesting link but, undocumented history is always subjected to a number of changes as well as distortion meant to twist some areas of interest for a purpose. However, I would want point out that Moyo, being one totem as it is, our ancestors created two different Totems originating from our original Moyondizvo and these are &quot;MOYO SINYORO&quot; and &quot;MOYO MUTURIKWA&quot;. These are sons of our daughters who had no totems and had to use Moyo though after they were granted authority.

About the Bulawayo history, my elders told me that one Ndebele descendant is Khumalo while the rest are people who used to stay under the  Rozvi and they gave examples of Mpofu being Mhofu, Ncube-Soko, Ngulube-Humba, Nyoni-Shiri, Dube being Samaita Tembo and so on. By this they were actually telling me that all people out there are Zimbabweans who were under Lozi before these invasions. 

Bhasvi, Nhenga, Mutinhima and Jiri should have been brothers if my memory serves me right, though I&#039;m not very certain. We  can further research on that and update. I&#039;m also of the opinion that we have our history stitched together from what is left of us so that our children will at least have somewhere to start from given that days are numbered and soon we will history.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m Bhasvi (Chibaya) from Wedza. Comparison of what I&#8217;m reading here to what I gathered from some elders that I happened to share time with only shows a very interesting link but, undocumented history is always subjected to a number of changes as well as distortion meant to twist some areas of interest for a purpose. However, I would want point out that Moyo, being one totem as it is, our ancestors created two different Totems originating from our original Moyondizvo and these are &#8220;MOYO SINYORO&#8221; and &#8220;MOYO MUTURIKWA&#8221;. These are sons of our daughters who had no totems and had to use Moyo though after they were granted authority.</p>
<p>About the Bulawayo history, my elders told me that one Ndebele descendant is Khumalo while the rest are people who used to stay under the  Rozvi and they gave examples of Mpofu being Mhofu, Ncube-Soko, Ngulube-Humba, Nyoni-Shiri, Dube being Samaita Tembo and so on. By this they were actually telling me that all people out there are Zimbabweans who were under Lozi before these invasions. </p>
<p>Bhasvi, Nhenga, Mutinhima and Jiri should have been brothers if my memory serves me right, though I&#8217;m not very certain. We  can further research on that and update. I&#8217;m also of the opinion that we have our history stitched together from what is left of us so that our children will at least have somewhere to start from given that days are numbered and soon we will history.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Bheki Moyo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-602</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Bheki Moyo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 12:06:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-602</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Jonathan Moyondizvo, there was no interim Ndebele ruler called Dingiswayo. The only Dingiswayo Zulu/ Nguni history tells us of is of the Mthethwa clan, the same one who mentored a young Shaka Zulu. Secondly, your argument that &quot;Dingiswayo&quot; and later Lobengula subdued the Karanga, in your words, the Shona living in Matebeleland is heavily flawed and a gross injustice. 
When Mzilikazi came to Zimbabwe and settled in his capital, Entumbane, he made peace with the Rozvi, abakaMambo and in fact Ndebele historians say he actually asked for a place to stay and he was referred to western Zimbabwe. This argument is supported by the fact that the Ndebele later went to pray at the Rozvi shrine together with their &quot;hosts&quot; at Njelele/Nzhelele. The word &quot;UMlimu&quot; in reference to God, is a corruption of the &quot;mudimu/modimo by the Ndebele.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jonathan Moyondizvo, there was no interim Ndebele ruler called Dingiswayo. The only Dingiswayo Zulu/ Nguni history tells us of is of the Mthethwa clan, the same one who mentored a young Shaka Zulu. Secondly, your argument that &#8220;Dingiswayo&#8221; and later Lobengula subdued the Karanga, in your words, the Shona living in Matebeleland is heavily flawed and a gross injustice.<br />
When Mzilikazi came to Zimbabwe and settled in his capital, Entumbane, he made peace with the Rozvi, abakaMambo and in fact Ndebele historians say he actually asked for a place to stay and he was referred to western Zimbabwe. This argument is supported by the fact that the Ndebele later went to pray at the Rozvi shrine together with their &#8220;hosts&#8221; at Njelele/Nzhelele. The word &#8220;UMlimu&#8221; in reference to God, is a corruption of the &#8220;mudimu/modimo by the Ndebele.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Nhaka yevaShona &#187; The Moyo people				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-358</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nhaka yevaShona &#187; The Moyo people]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 19:08:47 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-358</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[[&#8230;] Rozvi, like many other groups, say that they came from a land called Guruuswa and from a place called [&#8230;]]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[&#8230;] Rozvi, like many other groups, say that they came from a land called Guruuswa and from a place called [&#8230;]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Ross Talor				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-38</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross Talor]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 11:22:42 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-38</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[The Rozvi Empire really has a vast history. And by the way Mutendi is the adopted name of the Makuwa family.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Rozvi Empire really has a vast history. And by the way Mutendi is the adopted name of the Makuwa family.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Ross Talor				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-37</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross Talor]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 11:21:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-37</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[The Rozvi Empire really has a very huge history. And by the way Mutendi is the adopted name of the Makuwa family.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Rozvi Empire really has a very huge history. And by the way Mutendi is the adopted name of the Makuwa family.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: flixx mukaranga				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-36</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[flixx mukaranga]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 08:05:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-36</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[my realization of your story being fictional in some parts is your mention of  Mutendi family being decendants of the Rozvi rulers. if u knew any better u would have known that Mutendi is the adopted name of the Makuwa family!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>my realization of your story being fictional in some parts is your mention of  Mutendi family being decendants of the Rozvi rulers. if u knew any better u would have known that Mutendi is the adopted name of the Makuwa family!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Eddy				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-35</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Eddy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2015 18:42:40 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-35</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I HOPE PEOPLE TO STOP CONFUSING NGUNI OR ZULU HISTORY WITH THEIR OWN,SURNAME LIKE KHUMALO,NGWENYA,NDLOVU,NYATHI ARE ALL ORIGINALLY ZULU OR NGUNI SURNAMES AND PEOPLE WITH THOSE SURNAMES IN OTHER PARTS OF AFRICA ARE DESCENDANTS OF NGUNI&#039;S OR ZULU WHO CONQURED OTHER NATIONS OR MERGED WITH THEM.SINCE THE NGUNI LANGUAGE IS MOSTLY POKEN IN SOUTH AFRICA SOME WHO ENDERED UP IN OTHER COUNTRIES ENDED ABSORBING OTHER NATIONS LANGUAGES AND CULTURES WHEN THE EUROPEANS CAME AND THEY WHERE FORCED TO RELINQUISH THEIR DOMINANCE SINCE THE EURPEANS WHERE THE GREATER NEW POWER]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I HOPE PEOPLE TO STOP CONFUSING NGUNI OR ZULU HISTORY WITH THEIR OWN,SURNAME LIKE KHUMALO,NGWENYA,NDLOVU,NYATHI ARE ALL ORIGINALLY ZULU OR NGUNI SURNAMES AND PEOPLE WITH THOSE SURNAMES IN OTHER PARTS OF AFRICA ARE DESCENDANTS OF NGUNI&#8217;S OR ZULU WHO CONQURED OTHER NATIONS OR MERGED WITH THEM.SINCE THE NGUNI LANGUAGE IS MOSTLY POKEN IN SOUTH AFRICA SOME WHO ENDERED UP IN OTHER COUNTRIES ENDED ABSORBING OTHER NATIONS LANGUAGES AND CULTURES WHEN THE EUROPEANS CAME AND THEY WHERE FORCED TO RELINQUISH THEIR DOMINANCE SINCE THE EURPEANS WHERE THE GREATER NEW POWER</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Tangenhamo eka Nyahuma				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-34</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tangenhamo eka Nyahuma]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2014 06:55:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-34</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Moyo Mtyambizi ! Sahayi derives from the little earthenware pot in which delicacies like &quot; gwatakwata &quot; were cooked. The Rozvi man would pride himself that only he would be the recepient of the pot from the &quot; mvana &quot; hence their praise song &quot; mune mvana ndopinda runa !&quot; Basvi is a predecessor Mambo to Dhlembeu the renowned chief. He in turn got his nickname from the fact that he is reputed to have eaten the seed which should have been given to the Mamoyos for a blessing pre planting time! Zvakawoma Basvi ! &quot; Bula gango tibone kalino minya ! &quot;]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Moyo Mtyambizi ! Sahayi derives from the little earthenware pot in which delicacies like &#8221; gwatakwata &#8221; were cooked. The Rozvi man would pride himself that only he would be the recepient of the pot from the &#8221; mvana &#8221; hence their praise song &#8221; mune mvana ndopinda runa !&#8221; Basvi is a predecessor Mambo to Dhlembeu the renowned chief. He in turn got his nickname from the fact that he is reputed to have eaten the seed which should have been given to the Mamoyos for a blessing pre planting time! Zvakawoma Basvi ! &#8221; Bula gango tibone kalino minya ! &#8220;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Chivimbiso Njovo Moyo Msweli				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-33</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chivimbiso Njovo Moyo Msweli]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 10:24:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-33</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Could someone help me with the Moyo praise poem(Detembo remutupo wevarozvi).My late father used to prise the totem as Moyo,sayi,Dewa, vhumaranda, vakadzi vechiza vamene, vanokope chirimo chikave ndove, murambwa nehama vatorwa vachindida................................... something like this.Could someone help me with a proper one or something related to this.Its quite interesting to note we are too many of our clan.Please email me on chivimbison@gmail.com]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Could someone help me with the Moyo praise poem(Detembo remutupo wevarozvi).My late father used to prise the totem as Moyo,sayi,Dewa, vhumaranda, vakadzi vechiza vamene, vanokope chirimo chikave ndove, murambwa nehama vatorwa vachindida&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;.. something like this.Could someone help me with a proper one or something related to this.Its quite interesting to note we are too many of our clan.Please email me on <a href="mailto:chivimbison@gmail.com">chivimbison@gmail.com</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: manyears mdutshwa chuchu				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-32</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[manyears mdutshwa chuchu]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 16:55:07 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-32</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I HAVE WRITTEN THE CORRECT HISTORY OF ZIMBABWE

IT WILL TOUCH ON SOME NEIGHBOURING COUNTRIES

AT THE MOMENT I HAVE SUBMITTED IT TO THE PRESIDENT

OFFICE (ZIMBABWE)  VERY SOON IT WILL COME OUT

I HOPE THE TRUTH WILL SET YOU FREE 5/5/14]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I HAVE WRITTEN THE CORRECT HISTORY OF ZIMBABWE</p>
<p>IT WILL TOUCH ON SOME NEIGHBOURING COUNTRIES</p>
<p>AT THE MOMENT I HAVE SUBMITTED IT TO THE PRESIDENT</p>
<p>OFFICE (ZIMBABWE)  VERY SOON IT WILL COME OUT</p>
<p>I HOPE THE TRUTH WILL SET YOU FREE 5/5/14</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Mathumo Tapela Moyo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-31</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mathumo Tapela Moyo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2011 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-31</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Enerst Maruta is a shona lier who doesn’t know his history. At Ntabazinduna Mzilikazi was killing his chiefs(èr is no sunrise b4 sunset) Mzilikazi singed a peacetreaty with ‘our’ kingMAMBO thats why u can c even 2day no prob btwn è Kalanga,Venda,karanga,Tswana,Ndebele,Sotho and Jawunda.but when comes yesh]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Enerst Maruta is a shona lier who doesn’t know his history. At Ntabazinduna Mzilikazi was killing his chiefs(èr is no sunrise b4 sunset) Mzilikazi singed a peacetreaty with ‘our’ kingMAMBO thats why u can c even 2day no prob btwn è Kalanga,Venda,karanga,Tswana,Ndebele,Sotho and Jawunda.but when comes yesh</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Mathumo Tapela Moyo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-30</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mathumo Tapela Moyo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2011 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-30</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Shona name came with Ndebeles, there was nothing called shona b4 mzilikazi arrive but Kalanga/karanga,Lobedu. Venda are a mixture kalanga and Pedi. Most pedi are origional Zims.kalanga are è 1 built G Zim and another one in Bosti but small as a temple. Ask Kalangas/Venda most of them knows their Zim history. NOT A shona written lie]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Shona name came with Ndebeles, there was nothing called shona b4 mzilikazi arrive but Kalanga/karanga,Lobedu. Venda are a mixture kalanga and Pedi. Most pedi are origional Zims.kalanga are è 1 built G Zim and another one in Bosti but small as a temple. Ask Kalangas/Venda most of them knows their Zim history. NOT A shona written lie</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: kenny moyo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-29</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kenny moyo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 06:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-29</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[This is very interesting. I had heard that the Moyo clan were very accommodating, but all the other info about not accepting lobola, being one, Rozvi Kingdom and stuff like that, I had not really paid attention to. I think I’m going to spend more time now looking into this whole moyo business.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is very interesting. I had heard that the Moyo clan were very accommodating, but all the other info about not accepting lobola, being one, Rozvi Kingdom and stuff like that, I had not really paid attention to. I think I’m going to spend more time now looking into this whole moyo business.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: MuRozvi				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-15</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[MuRozvi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2011 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-15</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[The word Murozvi and my grandfather taught me comes from the warlike nature that the people who came to be know by that name had. Kurozva means to be made disappear. During the wars caused by the Rozvi, people would say “Akarozva nehondo”, meaning he perished in the war.VaRozvi as they are know today was not their name, their actual name I do not know. Rozvi is just a word in the shona langauge that the portuguese ended up using to call these people that had defeated them as a sign of respect.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The word Murozvi and my grandfather taught me comes from the warlike nature that the people who came to be know by that name had. Kurozva means to be made disappear. During the wars caused by the Rozvi, people would say “Akarozva nehondo”, meaning he perished in the war.VaRozvi as they are know today was not their name, their actual name I do not know. Rozvi is just a word in the shona langauge that the portuguese ended up using to call these people that had defeated them as a sign of respect.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: welly dhewa				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-28</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[welly dhewa]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2011 08:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-28</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[can someone tell me who were the brothers of Jiri, my oldman claims his great grand father was Jiri,s older brother. Is dewa, sai Moyondizvo one and the same thing?]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>can someone tell me who were the brothers of Jiri, my oldman claims his great grand father was Jiri,s older brother. Is dewa, sai Moyondizvo one and the same thing?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: senzeni				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-26</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[senzeni]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 00:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-26</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[moyo is shona]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>moyo is shona</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: herbert moyo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-27</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[herbert moyo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2011 19:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-27</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[this is stuff I have been looking for! thank you guys for the exchanges. My case is I am Moyo living in Matabeleland South, Zimbabwe, Oral history about us is that the clan is here due to someone who came from the east refered to as Mzungu, so we call ourselves AbeZungu, It is said that this ancestor came with his brothers who left him ill as they returned to the east as they were traders. He was to get well and work for the people who looked after him. They were impressed by his skill and gave him a wife. When his brothers came looking for him after the father had accused them of having murdered their brother, he refused to return because he could not leave his wife and children as their people refused to go with him to an unknown land. It is only known from oral history of the clan here that the great ancestor of this man was called “Machendeka”.possibly corrupted. Prise names of our clan are in Kalanga. This amazes me as five generations of this clan has been living east of the Kalanga speaking people that is before or the time when the Ndebele came to Present day Matabeleland. One of the intrigues in our praise names says”banhu bampumbu vakadzwale hova kuMaseka.”If there is anyone with a similar story to tell can we communicate. If there is anyone with clues to unravel the mystry of my origin can they help me. My email is abezungu3@yahoo.com I eagerly await something from someone who can come up with a clue.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>this is stuff I have been looking for! thank you guys for the exchanges. My case is I am Moyo living in Matabeleland South, Zimbabwe, Oral history about us is that the clan is here due to someone who came from the east refered to as Mzungu, so we call ourselves AbeZungu, It is said that this ancestor came with his brothers who left him ill as they returned to the east as they were traders. He was to get well and work for the people who looked after him. They were impressed by his skill and gave him a wife. When his brothers came looking for him after the father had accused them of having murdered their brother, he refused to return because he could not leave his wife and children as their people refused to go with him to an unknown land. It is only known from oral history of the clan here that the great ancestor of this man was called “Machendeka”.possibly corrupted. Prise names of our clan are in Kalanga. This amazes me as five generations of this clan has been living east of the Kalanga speaking people that is before or the time when the Ndebele came to Present day Matabeleland. One of the intrigues in our praise names says”banhu bampumbu vakadzwale hova kuMaseka.”If there is anyone with a similar story to tell can we communicate. If there is anyone with clues to unravel the mystry of my origin can they help me. My email is <a href="mailto:abezungu3@yahoo.com">abezungu3@yahoo.com</a> I eagerly await something from someone who can come up with a clue.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Ray				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-25</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ray]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2011 17:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-25</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Please help! is moyo dewa a shona, venda, ndebele surname, can someone tell the origin?, my email is: rnadoo1@webmail.co.za]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Please help! is moyo dewa a shona, venda, ndebele surname, can someone tell the origin?, my email is: <a href="mailto:rnadoo1@webmail.co.za">rnadoo1@webmail.co.za</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Claude Chibaya				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-24</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Claude Chibaya]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 08:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-24</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I wonder what information the history department at the university of Zimbabwe would have on all these things. Its a pity we never documented stuff, even today how far back can we go with our on history. If your kids were to ask you to go back 4 generations, how many of us can do that. I think we need to start documenting things, there is a starting point for everything. I am a Rozvi myself(Basvi), i come from Wedza. We used to fall under Chief Ruzane before independence (lozani).]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wonder what information the history department at the university of Zimbabwe would have on all these things. Its a pity we never documented stuff, even today how far back can we go with our on history. If your kids were to ask you to go back 4 generations, how many of us can do that. I think we need to start documenting things, there is a starting point for everything. I am a Rozvi myself(Basvi), i come from Wedza. We used to fall under Chief Ruzane before independence (lozani).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Tapiwa Moyo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-14</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tapiwa Moyo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 09:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-14</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Jonathan can you help me with the praise poem (detembo) of the Moyondizvo tribe . my email is tappsmoyo@gmail.com]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jonathan can you help me with the praise poem (detembo) of the Moyondizvo tribe . my email is <a href="mailto:tappsmoyo@gmail.com">tappsmoyo@gmail.com</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Tapiwa Moyo				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-23</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tapiwa Moyo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 09:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-23</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Can someone help me with the the praise poem (detembo) of the Moyo Dewa yeVarozvi . You can email it to tappsmoyo@gmail.com .]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Can someone help me with the the praise poem (detembo) of the Moyo Dewa yeVarozvi . You can email it to <a href="mailto:tappsmoyo@gmail.com">tappsmoyo@gmail.com</a> .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Edson Bhasvi				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-22</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Edson Bhasvi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2010 14:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-22</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[I like the way you people are analysing our history. all i know is that i am moyondizvo sai dhewa. Your analysis has revealed certain areas of interest for me and i now starting to research more about my History.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I like the way you people are analysing our history. all i know is that i am moyondizvo sai dhewa. Your analysis has revealed certain areas of interest for me and i now starting to research more about my History.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: khazamula baloyi				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-21</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[khazamula baloyi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2010 15:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-21</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[i think i am also a rozvi since my surname is valoyi- or valozvi or originally varozvi. i am also a karanga and my chieftainship at nwamitwa. valoyi and the lobedus are the surving rozvis in south africa. let us claim our kingdom of south africa, botswana and zimbabwe where the capital is at mapungubwe which is a national heritage site.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>i think i am also a rozvi since my surname is valoyi- or valozvi or originally varozvi. i am also a karanga and my chieftainship at nwamitwa. valoyi and the lobedus are the surving rozvis in south africa. let us claim our kingdom of south africa, botswana and zimbabwe where the capital is at mapungubwe which is a national heritage site.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Moyo Rusike				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-20</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Moyo Rusike]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 03:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-20</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Like most of you, I have tried to find as much as I could. It was when I read a book published in Rhodesia that stated that the Zimbabwe ruins could as old as 3000 years. My first reaction was, “There has to be a link with Ancient Egypt.”The prevalence of gold in modern-day Zimbabwe and use of gold by pharoahs had to be a clue. Prior to all this, I had started to read books on ancient Egypt I looked for the subtle things that others would normally miss. Everythinhg crystallized upon readingg Cheikh Anta Diop’s seminal book. Right off the cuff, he stated that the facial features of the Sphinx as drawn by Napoleon’s artist had unmistakeble Bantu features.Diop mentioned the fact that one cultural feature of ancient Egypt was the use of totems for identities. I then bought a book by Adolf Erman who wrote about the use of animal names as names of provinces (nomes). Among the animals considered sacred are (i) the crocodile, (ii) the baboon, (iii) falcon/eagle, (iv) dog, (v) cow, (iv) snake etc. These are our Ngwenya/Gushungo, Soko, Hungwe, Nkomo, Mheta.My point is that this part of our culture goes way way back. It is older that 1500 years. I think there is more that we do not know right now but by asking and talking to each other to share our knowledge, we could actually unravel our own history.Then this year the BBC had a special documentation on Africa’s lost Kingdoms]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Like most of you, I have tried to find as much as I could. It was when I read a book published in Rhodesia that stated that the Zimbabwe ruins could as old as 3000 years. My first reaction was, “There has to be a link with Ancient Egypt.”The prevalence of gold in modern-day Zimbabwe and use of gold by pharoahs had to be a clue. Prior to all this, I had started to read books on ancient Egypt I looked for the subtle things that others would normally miss. Everythinhg crystallized upon readingg Cheikh Anta Diop’s seminal book. Right off the cuff, he stated that the facial features of the Sphinx as drawn by Napoleon’s artist had unmistakeble Bantu features.Diop mentioned the fact that one cultural feature of ancient Egypt was the use of totems for identities. I then bought a book by Adolf Erman who wrote about the use of animal names as names of provinces (nomes). Among the animals considered sacred are (i) the crocodile, (ii) the baboon, (iii) falcon/eagle, (iv) dog, (v) cow, (iv) snake etc. These are our Ngwenya/Gushungo, Soko, Hungwe, Nkomo, Mheta.My point is that this part of our culture goes way way back. It is older that 1500 years. I think there is more that we do not know right now but by asking and talking to each other to share our knowledge, we could actually unravel our own history.Then this year the BBC had a special documentation on Africa’s lost Kingdoms</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Ernest Maruta				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-19</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ernest Maruta]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Sep 2010 14:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=62#comment-19</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[OUr Dinasty is like MY father Simbarashe, to Mafoti, Shumbanhete, Maruta, Mutinhima, Chirisamhuru (Who was the last Rozvi king skinned alive by the ndebele, based at the Matopos (Ntabayezinduna), Thats as far as i know my family tree.but my father sometimes call me Madzivanyika but I don’t how we are linked to madzivanyika.we are based in Bikita, Zimbabwe.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>OUr Dinasty is like MY father Simbarashe, to Mafoti, Shumbanhete, Maruta, Mutinhima, Chirisamhuru (Who was the last Rozvi king skinned alive by the ndebele, based at the Matopos (Ntabayezinduna), Thats as far as i know my family tree.but my father sometimes call me Madzivanyika but I don’t how we are linked to madzivanyika.we are based in Bikita, Zimbabwe.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
			</channel>
</rss>
