<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"

	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: The function of roora	</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../index.html</link>
	<description>A detailed history of the Shona people of Zimbabwe</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 17:02:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.2.2</generator>
			<item>
				<title>
				By: Athanasio Dzadagu				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-629</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Athanasio Dzadagu]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2017 00:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=1#comment-629</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[While appreciating the criticisms posted by the two above, I regret that I had not come across this piece of writing before writing my book on &quot;Zvinotevedzwa pakuroora kana kuroorwa: kugarisana kwevaroorana&quot;, which is already with the publishers. I could have refined an element or two. Thank you very much writer and critical commentators. We definitely need more of this. Athanasio Dzadagu.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While appreciating the criticisms posted by the two above, I regret that I had not come across this piece of writing before writing my book on &#8220;Zvinotevedzwa pakuroora kana kuroorwa: kugarisana kwevaroorana&#8221;, which is already with the publishers. I could have refined an element or two. Thank you very much writer and critical commentators. We definitely need more of this. Athanasio Dzadagu.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Tete Prim				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-534</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tete Prim]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 05:49:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=1#comment-534</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[Point on how Munyai informs father of bride about ceremony is wrong. It only applies in cases where the girl has eloped hence &#039;tsvakirai kuno&#039; translated look for her here. Normal would be Munyai approaches uncle of the girls and asks for date convenient to the family for the ceremony.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Point on how Munyai informs father of bride about ceremony is wrong. It only applies in cases where the girl has eloped hence &#8216;tsvakirai kuno&#8217; translated look for her here. Normal would be Munyai approaches uncle of the girls and asks for date convenient to the family for the ceremony.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
						<item>
				<title>
				By: Emmanuel Sheunesu				</title>
				<link>./../index.html#comment-421</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Emmanuel Sheunesu]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2016 11:35:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://localhost:8080/mashona.com/?p=1#comment-421</guid>
					<description><![CDATA[i think you erred under the heading &quot;how is roora determined&quot;. You ought have had regard to the various types of kuroora like kutizisa, kutema ugariri though nomore practised these days and kukumbira or kutumira. Under kutumira the munyayi goes and do some formalities of greetings and then introduces the subject with a statement like &quot;tine ruva rataona mubindu menyu ratifadza ratafunga kutanha tindodyarira kwedu&quot; or tauyawo kuzotsvaga sadza pano&quot; and this is understood to mean that the man is a messenger conveying a message of intended marriage of one of the daughters of the visited family. Note that word would have been passed prior to that notifying of the visit to pay roora and so the inlaws will be aware and waiting for vakwasha.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>i think you erred under the heading &#8220;how is roora determined&#8221;. You ought have had regard to the various types of kuroora like kutizisa, kutema ugariri though nomore practised these days and kukumbira or kutumira. Under kutumira the munyayi goes and do some formalities of greetings and then introduces the subject with a statement like &#8220;tine ruva rataona mubindu menyu ratifadza ratafunga kutanha tindodyarira kwedu&#8221; or tauyawo kuzotsvaga sadza pano&#8221; and this is understood to mean that the man is a messenger conveying a message of intended marriage of one of the daughters of the visited family. Note that word would have been passed prior to that notifying of the visit to pay roora and so the inlaws will be aware and waiting for vakwasha.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
						</item>
			</channel>
</rss>
